Inventory of the Reetika Vazirani Papers 1967-2008
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Personal and Professional Letters and Work, 1985-2006
  - Miscellaneous Professional Materials, 1989-2003 (3)
    - (3, 5)
      - "Whereabouts" Manuscript sent to Ethelbert Miller, December 1989 (3, 5)
        This folder contains a signed copy of Vazirani's manuscript titled, "Whereabouts," and the envelope in which it was sent.
      - Vazinrani Resumes and Promotional Materials, 1992?-2003 (3, 5, 4)
        This folder contains multiple versions of Vazirani's resume and various promotional materials relating to her work. Also included is an introduction for Vazirani written by Miller for an event at the Folger Shakespeare Reading festival called "Ascension #127" and a brief letter from Miller thanking her for agreeing to serve as a contributing editor for Poet Lore Magazine.
    Subseries 4: Death, Funeral, Legacy
  - Death, Funeral, Legacy, 2003-2006 (4)
    This sub-series contains materials that relate to Vazirani's death, funeral, and memorializing her life and work. They were sent to and collected by Miller.
    - (4, 5)
      - Articles on Vazirani's Death, 2003 (4, 5)
        This folder contains newspaper articles and printed internet articles on Vazirani's death.
      - Funeral Programs and Readings (with notes), 2003 (4, 5, 6)
        This folder contains multiple programs for Vazirani's funeral, as well as directions to the cemetery. It also includes a tribute, with notes, written by Miller for Vazirani and her son, Jehan Komunyakaa.
      - Vazirani Appreciation sent to Ethelbert Miller, 2003 (4, 5, 7)
        This folder contains condolence cards, letters, emails, poems, and an essay sent to Miller in memory of Vazirani.
      - Poetry, in Memoram, undated (4, 5, 8)
        This folder contains three poems written in honor of Vazirani, including "Cumin in the Eggs" by Ellen Berkovitch (three copies), "No More Suicides" by Sharon Olinka, and "Always Before, Light Gathered" by Jody Bolz.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence on Vazirani, 2003-2005 (4, 5, 9)
        This folder contains a number of printed emails concerning the publicity surrounding Vazirani's death as well as personal remembrances. Also included are a letter of thanks for a donation made by Miller to the Howard County Poetry and Literature Society in Vazirani's name and a greeting card with a photo from a mutual friend of Miller and Vazirani.
      - Heea Vazirani Fales to Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 2003-2006 (4, 5, 10)
        This folder contains three greeting cards and a letter sent to Miller by Heea Vazirani Fales, Reetika Vazirani's mother. They include brief personal details and references to organizing Vazirani's papers. The letter requests Miller's assistance in publishing Vazirani's work.
        Note: Additional correspondence between Heea Vazirani Fales and Ethelbert Miller can be found in Box 7 of the collection.
  Series 4: Personal Papers and Materials
- Personal Papers and Materials, 1973-2008
  This series contains materials relating to Vazirani's private life such as financial records, family correspondence, information her son, Jehan Komunyakaa, and originals and copies of legal documents. The series also includes a copy of Vazirani's suicide letter, and articles and condolences in regards to her death.
  Note: Additional personal items such as inspirational audio tapes, guest book, Vazirani's childhood choir book, sketchbook, and diploma from the University of Virginia may by found in Box 10 of the collection.
    Subseries 1: Financial Records
  - Financial Records, 1981-2005 (1)
    This sub-series contains Vazirani's financial records. It includes receipts, bank statements, housing information, and her insurance policy.
    - (1, 6)
      - Bank Statements and Account Information, 1985-2003 (1, 6)
        This folder contains Vazirani's bank and credit statements and account information.
      - Wellesley Financial Records, 1981-1988 (1, 6, 2)
        This folder contains Vazirani's loan and payment records from Wellesley College.
      - Miscellaneous Receipts and Financial Records, 1982-1988 (1, 6, 3)
        This folder contains various receipts and discount membership cards.
      - Notes and Receipts for Office Redecoration, 2002 (1, 6, 4)
        This folder contains receipts and notes from Vazirani's office redecoration.
      - Mortgage Documents, 2002-2003 (1, 6, 5)
        This folder contains Vazirani's mortgage and loan documents and information.
      - Mary Kay Consultant Agreement, 2003 (1, 6)
        This folder contains a letter and form confirming Vazirani's status as a Mary Kay consultant.
      - Moving Information and Records, 2003 (1, 6, 7)
        This folder contains contact information, notes, and two receipts for moving companies.
      - Housing Search for Emory Teaching Position, 2003 (1, 6, 8)
        This folder contains real estate services information and faxes regarding Vazirani's search for housing near Atlanta after she accepted a position at Emory University. Also included is a record of lease termination (she did not take the job).
      - Insurance Information, 2003-2005 (1, 6, 9)
        This folder contains Vazirani's insurance policy. Also included is claim information sent to her mother, Heea Vazirani Fales, after her death.
  - Correspondence, 1993-2003 (2)
    This sub-series contains letters, notes, and emails written by Vazirani on a range of personal topics.
    - (2, 6)
      - Family Correspondence, 1993-2003 (2, 6, 10)
        This folder contains a birthday card and three thank you cards Vazirani sent to her mother, Heea Vazirani Fales. Also included is a Mother's Day card from Vazirani's son, Jehan.
      - Correspondence from Vazirani, 2002-2003 (2, 6, 11)
        This folder contains letters, emails, and notes written by Vazirani on a variety of subjects to several different people. Of note, a printed email is included that describes how Vazirani was evicted from her Williamsburg apartment while teaching at William and Mary because of a change in ownership.
    Subseries 3: Personal Information and Records
  - Personal Information and Records, 1973-2003 (3)
    This sub-series contains a variety of materials relating to Vazirani's personal life. It includes photographs, awards, legal documents, and information on her son, Jehan Komunyakaa. A copy of Vazirani's suicide letter is also included.
    - (3, 6)
      - World Literacy of Canada Information Materials, 2001 (3, 6, 12)
        This folder contains information and promotional materials sent to Vazirani by World Literacy of Canada.
      - Institute for Professional Empoerments Coaching Worksheets and Notes, 2002 (3, 6, 13)
        This folder contains Vazirani's notes and worksheets from the Institute for Professional Empowerment Coaching program.
      - Awards and Honors, 1973-1998 (3, 6, 14)
        This folder contains certificates, letters, and newsclippings relating to Vazirani's personal and professional awards, honors, and achievements. Contents include: a poem on Martin Luther King, Jr. that won first prize in Vazirani's 5th grade class in 1973; information on the song, "Amazing Grace: The Police Officer's Tribute," Vazirani wrote with her former husband; and certificates for poetry awards and teaching positions.
      - Photographs, ?-2003 (3, 6, 15)
        This folder primarily contains various professional photographs of Vazirani. They vary in size, pose, and photographer, and most are not dated. There is a set of prints of Vazirani, Yusef Komunyakaa, and their son, Jehan. Photos from John Henley Photography have been removed from the envelopes, and there is a letter and an email included from the studio. Also included is a candid photograph from 2002 taken at a workshop in San Miguel de Allende, Mexico.
      - Divorce Settlement, 1995-1996 (3, 6, 16)
        This folder contains a fax copy of the divorce settlement between Vazirani and John T. Jordan.
      - Records on Jehan Komunyakaa (son), 2000-2003 (3, 6, 17)
        This folder contains birth records, social security card, health records and information, insurance documents, and care instructions for Vazirani's son, Jehan Komunyakaa. He also died July 16, 2003.
      - Miscellaneous Personal Information, 1984-2003 (3, 6, 18)
        This folder contains the following documents: Vazirani's social security card, voter registration card, a photocopy of her Certificate of Naturalization, vehicle registration information, and personal contact information.
      - Suicide Letter (photocopy), 2003 (3, 6, 19)
        This folder contains a photocopy of Vazirani's suicide letter. She died July 16, 2003.
    Subseries 4: Articles, Memorials, Condolences
  - Articles, Memorials, Condolences, 2003-2008 (4)
    This sub-series contains materials concerning Vazirani's death, funeral, and efforts to remember her life and work.
    - (4, 7)
      - Articles on Vazirani's Death, 2003 (4, 7, 1)
        This folder contains news articles on Vazirani's death. They include a section of The Washington Post, photocopied news clippings, and a printed version of an online article from an Indian American newspaper, India West.
      - Letter, Article, and Interview with Paula Span, Washington Post, 2003-2004 (4, 7, 2)
        This folder contains materials relating to Paula Span's Washington Post feature on Vazirani. They include Span's request for an interview with Vazirani's mother with two photocopies of previous issues of the Post Magazine, a transcript of an online chat with Span, and two copies of the front page of the Washington Post promoting the magazine.
      - The Washington Post Magazine (4 copies), 2004 (4, 7, 3)
        This folder contains four issues of the Washington Post Magazine, dated February 15, 2004. The profile on Vazirani, "The Falling Light," is on pages 16-21.
      - Callaloo Memorial (9 copies), 2004 (4, 7)
        This folder contains nine copies of a 2004 issues of Callaloo vol. 26, no. 2, published in Vazirani's memory.
      - Published Literary Memorials, 2003-2004 (4, 7, 5)
        This folder contains a variety of published memorials to Vazirani. They include seasonal publications by Copper Canyon Press, an issue of Arts & Letters Journal of Contemporary Culture, a copy of the Association of Writers and Writing Procatioms Job List, and three copies of "Poet's Choice" by Edward Hirsch.
      - Memorials and Donations, 2003-2008 (4, 7, 6)
        This folder contains letters and newsletters concerning donations and memorials made in Vazirani's name. They include letters from the William and Mary Alumni Association, Wellesley College, and the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation. Also included is a copy of the score for the song "Avatar," composed by Martha Mooke and dedicated to Vazirani's son, Jehan. A note from Yusef Komunyakaa is attached.
      - Condolences Sent to Heea Vazirani Fales, Reetika Vazirani's Mother, 2003-2004 (4, 7)
        This folder contains condolence cards and letters sent to Vazirani's mother, Heea Vazirani Fales.
      - Ethelbert Miller to Heea Vazirani Fales Correspondence, 2003-2008 (4, 7, 8)
        This folder contains letters, notes, emails, and poetry Ethelbert Miller sent to Heea Vazirani Fales. They focus primarily on coping with Vazirani's loss and remembering her life.
        Note: Additional correspondence between Heea Vazirani Fales and Ethelbert Miller can be found in Box 5 of the collection.
  Series 5: Miscellaneous Career and Personal Items
- Miscellaneous Career and Personal Items, 1967-2003
  This series contains a number of Vazirani's career-related and personal items, including floppy disks, a journal, index cards, name cards, a guest book, choir book, sketchbook, and a diploma.
  - (10)
    - Four Floppy Disks with Office Files, 1996-2002 (10)
      This envelope contains four floppy disks that hold a varity of Vazirani's work-related computer files. They include resumes, course syllabi, letters, essays, and a grant proposal.
    - Black Spiral Notebook, 2003 (10)
      This notebook includes journal entries, course notes for English 405/Anthropology 430: Descriptive Linguistics, French 406: Contemporary Spoken French, lecture notes, notes for Emory University, and drafts of poems.
    - Gray Box with Index Cards, 1990-2003 (10)
      This gray box contains a set of index cards that hold details on Vazirani's submissions to publishers and their contact information.
    - Inspirational Audio Tapes, 1997 (10)
      This box contains a set of four inspirational audio tapes by Dr. Al G. Salazar of the Divine Science Church. The titles are as follows: “A Plan for Living,” April 27, 1997; “The Great Healer,” June 22, 1997; “You Can Change Your Life,” August 24, 1997; “The Road to Fulfillment,” November 1997.
    - Name Cards, undated (10)
      This box includes a set of 13 name cards that read "Reetika Gina Vazirani."
    - Guest Book, undated (10)
      This box contains an undated purple and gold guest book.
    - Choir Workbook, 1967-1968 (10)
      This black three-ring binder contains Vazirani's childhood choir workbook from the First Presbyterian Church in Plattsburgh, New York. A note included by her mother dates the book from July (?) 1967 to October 1968, and mentions her birthday on August 9, 1962.
    - Green Sketchbook, 2001-2002 (10)
      This sketchbook contains a number of Vazirani's drawings for “Beginning” and “Beginning/Advanced Art” courses at the Watkins Institute.
    - Diploma, 1997 (10)
      This box contains Vazirani's diploma from the University of Virginia for her master's degree in Fine Arts for Creative Writing.